<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hidden things of Esau brought to light, and reproved in an answer to a book intituled A true relation of a dispute between Francis Fulwood, minister of West Alvington, in the county of Devon, and Thomas Salthouse, as it is said, of the county of Westmerland, before the congregation of them called Quakers, in the house of Henry Pollexpher Esquire, in the said parish of West. Published in the truth's defence, and sent abroad in the world, to pursue the unknown authors imperfect relation. By a follower of the Lamb in the war against the Beast and false prophet, known to the world by the name of Thomas Salthouse.</title>
            <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E912_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116537</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116537)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 137:E912[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hidden things of Esau brought to light, and reproved in an answer to a book intituled A true relation of a dispute between Francis Fulwood, minister of West Alvington, in the county of Devon, and Thomas Salthouse, as it is said, of the county of Westmerland, before the congregation of them called Quakers, in the house of Henry Pollexpher Esquire, in the said parish of West. Published in the truth's defence, and sent abroad in the world, to pursue the unknown authors imperfect relation. By a follower of the Lamb in the war against the Beast and false prophet, known to the world by the name of Thomas Salthouse.</title>
                  <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread Eagle neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693. --  True relation of a dispute, between Francis Fullwood minister of West-Alvington in the county of Devon, and one Thomas Salt-House, as 'tis said, of the county of Westmerland: before the congregation of them, called Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116537:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116537:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Hidden things of <hi>Eſau</hi> brought to light, And Reproved in an ANSWER To a Book Intituled <hi>A true Relation of a Diſpute between</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Fulwood, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Weſt Alvington, <hi>in the County of</hi> Devon, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Salthouſe, <hi>as it is ſaid, of the County of</hi> Weſtmerland, <hi>before the Congregation of them called</hi> Quakers, <hi>in the Houſe of</hi> Henry Pollexpher <hi>Eſquire, in the ſaid Pariſh of</hi> Weſt.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed in the Truth's defence, and ſent abroad in the World, to purſue the unknown Authors imperfect Relation.</p>
            <p>By a Follower of the LAMB in the War againſt the Beaſt and Falſe Prophet, known to the World by the name of <hi>Thomas <hi rend="underline">Salthouſe.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the Disputer of this world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this world?
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 1.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Thou haſt truſted in thy wickedneſs; thou haſt ſaid, None ſeeth me: Thy wiſdom and thy knowledge, it hath perverted thee.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iſai. 47.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine enemy; when I fall, I ſhall ariſe; when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord will be a light unto me.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Micah 7.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread-Eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116537:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116537:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as there came lately to my hands a certain Book, or rather a Libel without any name unto it, intituled, <hi>A true Relation, &amp;c.</hi> which it ſeems the Authors thereof, being conſcious of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs, vain Repetitions, and manifold Lies therein contained, durſt not own the ſame ſo far as to ſet their names thereunto, that ſo an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer might have been directed particularly to them and their folly made manifeſt; but thinking to ſhelter themſelves in the dark from the eye of man, thereby to keep their deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from the light: Yet he that ſearcheth the heart, and tries the reins, and brings the hidden things of <hi>Eſau</hi> to light, in his due time will bring them to Judgment, both for their evil thoughts, hard ſpeeches, and ungodly deeds; and this is he of whom I am a witneſs, who pleads the cauſe of the Innocent, and executes Righteous Judgment on the Earth.</p>
            <p>And although for that the Authors thus hide themſelves in the dark by concealing their names, and alſo the matters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, being of ſo little weight, it might juſtly have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed an Anſwer, yet notwithſtanding for the ſimple ſake, and Truths vindication, I am conſtrained to ſend this enſuing Anſwer into the World, eſpecially into the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> and Pariſh of <hi>Weſt Alvington,</hi> where it is likely theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Authors Relation have paſt before; that if poſſible, it might come to the view of ſome of them who have digged ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116537:3"/>deep to hide themſelves and their counſel in the dark, leſt their ſhame and nakedneſs ſhould be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Their Book or Libel being filled with ſo many vain Repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and groſs untruths of their own Suggeſtions, the Reader thereof can expect little for his Information or Edification: And therefore I ſhall not endeavor to fill a volumn with repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overmuch of what is herein contained; but onely hint at ſome paſſages that may ſeem to bear the moſt weight, and alſo manifeſt and reprove ſome of their lyes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116537:3"/>
            <head>Theſe Authors begin their Book as follows, <hi>A True Relation, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt ſentence is a lye, as I ſhall prove by your words in the <hi>Preface</hi> your own Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; where you confeſs you have conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Infirmities, Repetitions, and vile Speeches, which indeed were many, as you ſay; alſo you ſay, the Quaker was ſo full of Impertinencies and Repetitions, that his words here ſet down, ſeem to bear no proportion to his tedious and rude Diſcourſes: And then how can your Relation be true, when by your own confeſſion, much is omitted? out of your own mouths be you judged. And though you finde me rude in Speech, yet may you not expect to find me ſo in knowledge; for God hath given me a mouth and wiſdom to anſwer ſuch gain-ſayers and oppoſers, as call evil good, and good evil.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>On Tueſday</hi> 24 <hi>October,</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There was no ſuch day in the year; for the 24 day of <hi>October,</hi> 1656. was the ſixth day of the week, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friday, and the ſame day I was at a meeting in <hi>Plimouth;</hi> but I let this paſs among your other infirmities, though I might call it a lye. Its very unlike your Relation ſhould be true, when you could not ſo much as remember the day.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>Publiſhed by ſome that were preſent at the dispute, out of a ſingle and ſincere deſire, that Error may be aſhamed, and the truth cleared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw</hi> Error is aſhamed; for are you not aſhamed to own your Relation, which is ſo full of Error, although you ſay you were preſent at the diſpute? if not, why did not you ſubſcribe your names to your Book, which is ſo full of error. How can lyers clear the truth? its clear ready, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your deceit and deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, with which you would darken the truth, and caſt a ſtumbling
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116537:4"/>block before the ſimple, by rendring the truth odious; but the wo is unto ſuch as you, who call truth error, and error truth; that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs; a deceived heart hath led you aſide; a lye is in your right hand.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>It ſeemeth ſtrange unto ſome that Mr.</hi> Fulwood <hi>would venture to go to the Quakers meeting, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Its manifeſt, both of what generation you are of, and alſo him whom you call Mr. <hi>Fulwood:</hi> Your ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth you; did not you call him a Miniſter? when were any of Chriſts Miniſters called of Men, Maſter? and who were they that were ſo called? are not they tranſgreſſors of the command of Chriſt that call men ſo? Read <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. Why ſhould not he venture, unleſs he had thought the Quakers were ſuch as the men of his generation, who hate and beat in their Meeting places and carry before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and to priſon? or was he not rather conſcious to himſelf of his guilt and hypocriſie? <hi>For the ſinners in</hi> Sion <hi>are afraid, fearfulneſs ſurpriſeth the Hypocrites,</hi> Iſai. 33.14.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>He had no thought of making a ſet diſpute of it, till provoked by the Quakers railing diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here I call you to bear witneſs againſt your ſelves, that my diſcourſe was not railing, but words of truth and ſoberneſs, tending to the informing of the mindes of thoſe that were preſent at the ſaid meeting; that whereas they had formerly ſpent their money for that which was no bread, and their labor for that which did not ſatisfie; they might be turned to him who filleth the hungry with good things, and freely adminiſters out of the Everlaſting Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, without money, and without price: And as they had formerly in the time of their ignorance, heaped up to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Teachers, they were exhorted to turn from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the light; that ſo they might come to know the true Teacher <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Everlaſting, High Prieſt, the chief Shepherd and Biſhop of their Souls: There being many that day preſent, as ſheep without a Shepherd, unto whom I was moved to lay open the deceit of the blinde Guides, Idol-Shepherds,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116537:4"/>ſuch as run, but the Lord never ſent them, hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, falſe Prophets, deceivers and Antichriſts; ſuch as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine for money, and ſpeak a divination of their own brain; of which ſort, many are gone forth into the world in theſe laſt days, and perilous times; and many have followed their pernitious ways, by reaſon whereof the truth hath been evil ſpoken of; and unleſs you call the Scripture language, rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, own your ſelves to be falſe accuſers; for it lies upon you yet to prove what your falſe Relation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms.</p>
            <p>Book. 1: <hi>We hear the Quaker threatens to print the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate himſelf, from whom we can expect no faithfulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your firſt Reaſon is grounded on a lye, or falſe information at the beſt: I never threatened, nor indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any ſuch thing here; your evil ſurmiſing appears; your clearly manifeſt the contrary in your ſelves, which you ſay, you could not expect from me; for if I had firſt print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you might have found more faithfulneſs then I finde at your hands. But to me this is not ſtrange, ſeeing it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of what generation you are; had you not reſpected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, you would have done to me, as you would I ſhould have done to you, and not to have added to, nor diminiſhed from my words, to make them appear ridiculous to the Reader, when you pretend to give a true Relation; but your covering is too narrow, though you have made haſte with your work, leſt others ſhould have written before, that would have dealt equally for both parties.</p>
            <p>Book. 2. <hi>We hear that ſome others who did not write ſay, They will lay their heads together, and print as much as they can remember; which if they ſhould, it muſt needs be done very imperfectly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You have left enough for them yet to do (if any ſuch intention were) before the Relation be perfect; and they may either write or print, notwithſtanding what you have done: And if they ſhould give a more imperfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation then you have done, I ſhall deny both you and them, and ſtand a witneſs for God againſt you all; but this I know
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116537:5"/>there is none that owns the truth in the leaſt meaſure, that was preſent that day, though the words were not written that day as they were ſpoken, that will joyn with or approve of what you have done. For they may plainly ſee your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal ballance, and bag of deceitful weights, and how you have wreſted my words, and enlarged upon his, as if your works ſhould never have been brought to light, or you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in queſtion to give an account thereof; but the juſt God ſees you in ſecret, who will reward you openly.</p>
            <p>Book. 3. <hi>We hear that ſince we ſuppoſed, prejudiced perſons are ready to ſay, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That they were prejudiced perſons who ſaid ſo, is nothing but your ſuppoſition; and if they ſaid I had, the beſt they might ſpeak truth, for truth prevails againſt deceit, and the Lamb muſt have the victory: There is little reaſon, that what you ſuppoſe, wonder at, or affirm, ſhould gain much credit or change their mindes, though for the preſent you have endeavored to caſt a miſt before the eyes of ſuch as heard not both parties that day, to beget a prejudice in their mindes againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>Let none ſlander us with unfaithfulneſs in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſay that the Relation is unfaithful and falſe, is no ſlander. It ſeems you were convinced in Conſcience of your guilt in this thing, elſe why did you conceal your names? had you given the whole Reaſon on both ſides, as you ſay you did, you need not have been aſhamed to own it, or put it to others that would have remembred more, and yet are you ſo impudent as to call it a true Relation.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>Yea, the weight of Mr.</hi> Fulwoods <hi>Anſwer, though extemporary, is ſuch that we think we may ſafely, let them looſe not onely to what was ſaid that day, but to what can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied upon the deliberation of all the Quakers, betwixt this and</hi> Weſtmerland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You have manifeſted your ſelves in this Relation to the leſt of theſe called Quakers, to be proud boaſters; and to ſuch as live in the light, his Anſwers, though with the aſſiſtance of his, and your deliberation appear to be light
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116537:5"/>and vain; although you that are deſtroyed for want of knowledge, and ſet your ſelves to contend for, and uphold ſuch as cry peace, while men put into their mouths, ſay they are weighty; and by the aſſiſtance and direction of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit of him who gives a mouth and wiſdom to his Children, that all their adverſaries are not able to gainſay or reſiſt; I ſhall anſwer to ſome of his weighteſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though it may be not with ſuch cunning deviſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and excellence of Speech, as is pleaſing to your ears as cannot endure found doctrine; and yet of as much and more weight and uſe for edification to the ſimple, as your Narrative, which you ſay, you have humbly put before them; your expreſſions manifeſt but little humility.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>If any ſhall print another Narrative, let them but be faithful in ſetting down Mr.</hi> Fulwoods <hi>own Anſwers or Arguments, in their due weight and fulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ye Hipocrites, will you pull a mote out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others eye, while the beam is in your own? you that would teach others, would not you teach your ſelves? it would be but vain repetitions to write his words over again. Ought not you to have been faithful firſt, in ſetting down my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers and Arguments, with the due weight and fulneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you had exhorted others to faithfulneſs in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and then there had been no need of another Relation; but the ſteddy eye (as you ſay) of thoſe before whom you put your Narrative, might have taken a full view of the truth on both ſides, as their ears had done before, who were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at that diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>We know not that we have concealed any thing, ſave ſome infirmities,</hi> viz <hi>Reproaches and vile Speeches, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were ſuch, and ſo many, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh you deceitful tongues! do you pretend a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing of infirmities, reproaches, and vile ſpeeches, and yet mention them in general, which ſuch aggravating circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as to be ſuch and ſo many, as even inforced ſome of Mr. <hi>Fulwoods</hi> more ingenious adverſaries, to ſay, That they wondred that fleſh and blood could contain ſo long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch temptations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What were thoſe reproaches
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116537:6"/>and vile ſpeeches, had it not have been as much Charity to have expreſt the particulars, as to mention them in general with ſuch aggravations? Let that in your conſciences wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whether you intended any ſuch thing as to conceal my infirmities and vile ſpeeches; if any had been uttered, were not thoſe the vile ſpeeches as you mention; the diſcovery of the deceit of the hirelings and falſe Prophets, which if you ſhould have ſet down, would have manife ſted the folly and wickedneſs of him, and that generation which you go about to hide and uphold?</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>There were ſome things very remarkable, and the cunning craftineſs of the Quaker was ſuch, That do what Mr.</hi> Fulwood <hi>could to force him to it, he ſtill found ſome trick or other to evade the maintaining thoſe paſſages (of dangerous conſequence) which he let fall in his firſt diſcourſe, which were not a few; and which he took notice Mr.</hi> Fulwood <hi>wrote down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> O ye deceitful Craftſmen, and falſe Accuſers, what were theſe paſſages of dangerous conſequence? was it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring againſt ſin, and exhorting to purity and holineſs, to minde the light, and take up the Croſs and follow Chriſt in the ſtraight way? or was it the laying open the deceit of the falſe Prophets, hirelings, and ſuch as ſay they are Miniſters of Chriſt, and are not? ſuch as are called of Men Maſter, take the cheif Seats in the Aſſemblies, uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts; and whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covetous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, and have forſaken the right way, and are gone in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for gifts and rewards: If he that you call Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> wrote down any thing of dangerous conſequence, it had been his duty or yours in this Relation, to have publiſhed them; that ſo they might have been avoided, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor aſhamed; for you ſay this was publiſhed out of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deſire, that truth might be cleared, and error aſhamed. And here you have added another lye, to ſay, That I took notice that Mr. <hi>Fulwood</hi> wrote down thoſe paſſages of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence; for I did not ſee him, nor any other write any thing that day of that diſcourſe, which I was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116537:6"/>moved of the Lord to ſpeak, not fearing all that came to oppoſe themſelves: Although I were ſenſible there were many that day come together to lie in wait to catch me in my words; and if I had ſeen any write down what I ſaid that day, I had no cauſe to be afraid nor aſhamed, knowing that I have a witneſs in all your conſciences that heard me, even the Authors of his Book, though they manifeſted themſelves to be my ſubtil Adverſaries; their cunning will deceive them in the end as their deceit comes to be laid open by the light; which makes manifeſt every mans work, of what ſort it is.</p>
            <p>Book. 2. <hi>He took all occaſions to bring the dispute to ſuch points as lay in difference between us and the Anabaptiſts, that thus he might engage the Anabaptiſts with himſelf, which indeed he effected, the greateſt advantage he got that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Have you no other reſuge but lies to ſhelter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? what occaſion took I to engage the Anabaptiſts? both they and moſt of the company then preſent ſaw the deceit of <hi>Francis Fulwood</hi> that day, and many of them declared againſt it. I utterly deny, that I endeavored to engage any further then the truth convinced them; neither did I fear any that did engage againſt me: And if the Lord raiſed up a witneſs in thoſe you call Anabaptiſts, or any others, to contend for the truth againſt your deceit, let him have the glory. I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire no mans perſon, becauſe of advantage; and if <hi>Francis Fulwood</hi> loſt the advantage that day with your aſſiſtance, or likely with the help of his Brethren of the Craft, he may think to regain what he then loſt, by enlarging upon his confuſed Anſwers and Arguments, and diminiſhing, and wreſting my Anſwers, Replies, and Arguments that day, made in the truths defence; but neither yours nor the as formed weapons ſhall proſper, your refuge of lies the Lord will ſweep away.</p>
            <p>Book. 3. <hi>That upon every ſtand or difficulty, he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fled unto the common Refuge of Hireling taking Tithes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Its a better refuge then lies to flie unto; did not the true Prophets, Miniſters, and Meſſengers of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116537:7"/>againſt hirelings, ſuch as divined for money, bare rule by their means; ſought for their gain from their quarter; and againſt covetous, proud, heady, high-minded men: Is <hi>Francis Fulwood</hi> guilty of any of theſe? If ſo, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in time, and turn you from him; if not, neither he nor you need be offended at me, nor account it too grateful a diſcourſe to any.</p>
            <p>Book. 4. <hi>Although he firſt urged to have the expreſs words of Scripture, to be the rule of the dispute, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You ſtill flie to your old refuge which cannot long ſtand, to wit lies; look back to the third remarkable thing, as you call it, and compare it with this, and your contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and confuſions will appear remarkable indeed: Did not you there ſay, that in every ſtand I fled to the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of Tithes, Hirelings, Diviners for money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are expreſs words of Scripture; and are you now ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to ſay, that I did not ſo much as once keep ſo exactly to the expreſs words of Scripture? Here you have given an opportunity ſufficiently to diſcover and lay open your folly.</p>
            <p>Book 5. <hi>Yet his cunning deceived him, in that as is moſt remarkable. The very Texts which he urged as before noted, afforded ſo direct and plain Anſwers upon every occaſion, that he had no room left for any colourable Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What can you not open your mouths without ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? I need give no other anſwer to this, but appeal to all thoſe that heard the diſpute, whoſe judgments are not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated with prejudice. Where are thoſe plain Anſwers? how is it you had not ſet down ſome of them, in that which you call a true Relation? A Reply that had not given ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, might ſtand for a colour; but as troups of Robbers that lay in wait to murder by conſent, you bend your tongues for lies, and ſhoot out your arrows, even bitter words.</p>
            <p>Book. 6. <hi>Lastly. And which did juſtly amaze us, how boldly, and with what inforcing Repetitions did Mr.</hi> Fulwood <hi>challenge him to ſet down his opinions, and engage that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he would at the next meeting bring Papiſts Books, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116537:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All opinions and ſects I deny, neither can I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member at preſent, that I heard him ſpeak of writing down any but my principles; what I owned and diſowned, I free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared that day, which neither be nor you hath or can diſprove; that diſpute being the Fourteenth day of the Moneth, called <hi>October,</hi> 1656. I had three meetings the ſame Moneth, one at the houſe of <hi>Henry Pollexphen</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid on the Six and twentieth day, another the Seven and twentieth at <hi>Batſon,</hi> and another the Eight and twentieth at <hi>Kingsbridge:</hi> of which, its likely <hi>Francis Fulwood</hi> had notice: For <hi>Nicholas Tripe,</hi> in whoſe houſe the Meeting then was, informed me, that he ſent a Meſſenger to him with a Meſſage to this purpoſe; That if he were diſſatisfied in any thing in the forementioned diſcourſe, he might have free liberty to come into his houſe, and be anſwered to what he had to object; which was done at my requeſt: Let his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and mine be judged by the Light, which is nearer to Popery, and who it was that fainted.</p>
            <p>Book. <hi>The Lord awaken us betime, leaſt we ſay peace peace, when ſudden deſtruction cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let him that nameth the name of the Lord, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity; for none calls Jeſus Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt. What have you to do to take his name into your mouths? and thus bend your tongues for lies, and hate to be reformed, upon you that are aſleep, will the day of the Lord come as a theif in the night, even as ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the Almighty. Therefore ariſe and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, and prepare to meet the Lord by repentance; that if peradventure the thoughts of your hearts may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given you. For the Lord hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt; and with equity will he plead the cauſe of the innocent, againſt whom you make war, and ſhoot your arrows in ſecret; fear and tremble, weep and howl, for the miſery that is coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; in flames of fire will God render vengeance upon his adverſaries; out of Heaven will he thunder upon them, and they ſhall be even broken to peeces, as the Veſſel of a Potter is broken with a rod of Iron. In vain do ye pot-ſheards
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116537:8"/>of the Earth ſtrive to ſet Bryers and Thorns in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; your formed weapons cannot proſper, a conſumption is even determined upon the whole Earth; and every mans work is to be tried by fire, that the approved of God may be made manifeſt. Can ye contend with the Almighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom all Nations are as the drop of a Bucket, or as the ſmall duſt of the ballance? Give over, ſtop your mouths; let all fleſh be ſilent before the Lord. Come down and ſit in the duſt, you that are high and lifted up, and meet the Judge by the way. Kiſs the Son, leaſt he be angry, and lay down your Crown at the feet of the Lamb; and let the Lord be your fear, and let him be your dreads; and let the light of Chriſt in your conſciences, try your words and works; and ceaſe from your blinde Leaders, that have uſed their tongues, and not profited the people. And while you have the light, believe in the light, and know, while the Spirit of the Lord ſtrives with you; reſiſt not his power, leſt your Bonds be made ſtrong, and you for ever ſhut up in utter darkneſs. A price is put into your hands, the Lord will not the death of a ſinner; the times of ignorance God winked at, but now he calls all men every where to repent. Call not this the railing diſcourſe, but take it as a Call to you, and a warning from the Lord, by a ſervant of the Truth, made willing by the power of God, to follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Salthouſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116537:8"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Francis Fulwood.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO the ſubſtance of what paſſed between thee and me, in the diſcourſe upon the Four and twentieth day of the Eight Moneth, 1656. in the houſe of <hi>Henry Pollexphen,</hi> which its like thou waſt not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the Printing of, if no: the cheifeſt actor. I ſhall return ſomething in Anſwer for the Truth's vindication, eſpecially to the particulars of moſt concernment, which I call to minde ſince I ſaw this Relation.</p>
            <p>As firſt: After I had ſpoken to the people that day, as I was moved, and directed by the Spirit of Truth; then a Friend of mine being moved alſo, ſtood up according to the order in the Churches of the Saints, and ſpoke to the people then preſent; to whom I gave liberty, the ſpirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets being made ſubject to the Prophets: And as thou mayeſt remember thy firſt Objection was againſt her for ſaying, <hi>Eternal life was not to be found in the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing was a Quere by me propounded to thee, which I yet received no ſatisfactory Anſwer unto, from thee.</p>
            <p>The third thing was an Objection made by thee againſt me, for expreſſing as I was declaring to the people, That thoſe who are out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, as they were then deſcribed by their fruirs and marks, were ſuch as Preach another Goſpel then that which the Apoſtle had preached; and ſo under the curſe, as it is written, <hi>Gal</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing was about the light ſpoken of in <hi>Johns</hi> Declaration, and ſomething concerning Tithes.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Concerning Baptiſm, and the words <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou,</hi> which many are offended at, as they are, and were given
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116537:9"/>and taken by the ſervants of God, one to another, as we read in the Scriptures of Truth.</p>
            <p>To theſe things in order, as God doth direct. I ſhall for the truths ſake anſwer; and as for the other paſſages in the Relation, not worth the taking notice of, or repeating over again, I ſhall let them ſtand and wither as an untimely birth, begotten by one of the adulterate generation, and brought forth of the womb of conſuſion.</p>
            <p>I might have written down a groſs ſum of lies; but it feems the Authors were pricked at the heart, when they ſaw what they had done; and ſo to hide themſelves, have concealed their names from the viſible eye of man: But this Cave of earthly ſubtilty, will not long hide them from the All-ſeeing eye of him with whom we have to do.</p>
            <p>If thou be one of their confederacy, fear and tremble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and come forth to the Light, that thou mayſt be proved and tried; and be not thou called of men Maſter, but learn of Jeſus Chriſt to be meek and lowly; take up his Croſs and follow him, and ſide not longer with the Chief Prieſts againſt him and his Miniſters, whom he hath ſent forth as ſheep among wolves, to reprove ſin in the Gates, and to preach Repentance, that people may be turned from the darkneſs to the light, and from under Satans power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; who hath appointed a day, in the which he will judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe particulars I ſhall proceed. Thy firſt Objection which the Book alſo mentions againſt the Woman, is as follows.</p>
            <p>Fulwood. I <hi>Have one word first unto this woman that ſpake laſt, and that is to charge her with ſpeaking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt the Scripture: She told us, that Eternal life was not to be found in the Scriptures; whereas the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly, that the holy Scriptures are able to make wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture is plain for what ſhe intended, <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>Search the Scriptures; for in them ye think to have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116537:9"/>life, and they are they that teſtifie of me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt. But <hi>ye will not come unto me, that you may have life.</hi> And again he ſaith, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life; and he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son, hath not life,</hi> although he may have the Scriptures:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10.</note> For the Miniſter of Chriſt waited for, and witneſſed the life of Chriſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in his mortal Body, and travailed again in birth with others, till Chriſt the Life was formed in them; <hi>I in them, and they in me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17. And Chriſt in you the Hope of glory, the Myſtery that hath been hid from ages and generations; and this is Life eternal, ſaith Chriſt to his Father, that they may know thee the onely true God and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent. For that which may be known of God, is manifeſt in them; and this is plain, That eternal life is not to be found in the Scriptures, although it is acknowledged they teſtifie of theſe things. Here is no mention made, That eternal life is to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and thus thy Objection is anſwered.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>True; but this Son in whom eternal life is, is alone to be found in Scriptures, as the next words affirm, They are they which teſtifie of me; therefore eternal life is to be found in the Scriptures. And thus your own Text overthrows you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Be not haſty, but look back to thy confuſed ſtuff, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth the Text overthrow me? for what the Scripture ſaith, own; but neither by this Text, nor any other. Canſt thou ever prove, that eternal life is to be found in the Scriptures? or the Son whom to know is eternal life; therefore let thy mouth be ſtopped, and proceed no farther to pervert the right ways of God, nor to wreſt the Scriptures to thy own deſtruction; for they are of no private interpretation; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many who have them, think to finde eternal life in them, both thou and they are deceived, that ſeek the living among the dead; for the letter killeth,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6.</note> but the ſpirit alone giveth life: He that hath underſtanding, let him read.</p>
            <p>The Scripture being thus plain againſt thy Objection, thy next ſhift was this; The Apoſtle ſaith expreſly; That the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116537:10"/>Scriptures are able to make wiſe unto ſalvation: But this was not to the thing in hand; for the Scriptures I own and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be profitable for Doctrine and Reproof, and to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Man of God perfectly; and through Faith, which is alone in Jeſus Chriſt, are they able to make wiſe unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and without Faith, its impoſſible to pleaſe God. And the company ſeeing the Objection anſwered, ſaid, Leave this, here is an end of it: And my Quere to thee was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, Whether is it lawful for a Miniſter of Chriſt to take Tithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, hire, gifts, or rewards, for preaching the Goſpel in theſe days, ſince the Law and the Prieſthood was changed, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>You think you have put a Queſtion that will gravel me; have but a little patience, and this will have its place. I demand of you, Whether the Scripture in the expreſs Letter of it, ſhall be our rule? or whether we may draw conſequences from it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny thy conſequences and meanings, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate interpretations; anſwer thou my Quere by plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>He may be a lawful Miniſter that takes hire; prove the contrary if you can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is no anſwer to my Quere; yet I ſhall prove the contrary by Scriptures. The Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch for hire, and by their means they bear rule, and my people love to have it ſo, ſaith the Lord. This was a wonderful horrible thing that was then committed in the Land, and not lawful; And for this cauſe, ſaith the Lord, ſhall <hi>Zion</hi> be ploughed as a field, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall become heaps, and the mountain of the houſe as the high places of the foreſt: They run, but I never ſent them, ſaith the Lord, therefore they ſhall not profit this people at all; night ſhall be unto them, that they ſhall not have a viſion, and the day ſhall be dark over them;
<note place="margin">Micah 3.</note> then ſhall the Seers be aſhamed, and the Diviners confounded; they ſhall all cover their lips, for there is no anſwer of God; they have fed themſelves with the fat, and cloathed themſelves with the wool; and my people are deſtroyed for want of knowledge,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116537:10"/>as troups of robbers wait for a man; even ſo the company of Prieſts murder in the way by conſent. Put into their mouths, and they cry peace, peace. Put not into their mouths, and they bite with their teeth, and even prepare war againſt them. This is not the lawful Miniſtry; for the wo is gone forth againſt the men that do this, both the Maſter and the Schollar; and he that helpeth, and he that is holpen, ſhall fall together. Therefore all people every where come out from among them, and be ye ſeparated, hold them not up, nor be partakers with them in their ſins; that ſo you may eſcape the miſery that is coming upon thoſe blind guides that have forſaken the way of the true Prophets, Chriſt and his Miniſters; who called all men to come freely without money, and without price, and abode in the truth, and gave freely as they had freely received, a neceſſity being laid upon them to preach the Goſpel freely, and to make it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge. Is this thy practiſe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> or doſt not thou preach for hire?</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>If I do, I have Scripture for it, and you cannot ſay I preach for hire, unleſs you could ſee my heart; and beſides my preaching twice every Lords day, which is all I am bound by man unto, I Catechiſe, I Expound upon ſome part of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I deſire particular Conference, in order to the Sacrament, I viſit the ſick, I preach my turn at ſome Lectures, and this day I am here doing more then I am bound to do, or can expect any reward from man; for ye all know I might have been quiet in my Study at home, but for love to the Souls of my poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that if poſſibly I might ſave them out of the hands of ſuch Deceivers and Seducers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou art upon thy Self-juſtification, yet art thou not clear, from being an hiteling; for thou haſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged thy ſelf to be bound by man, and alſo thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeſt thou hadſt a competent maintenance in lieu of Preaching. What command or example haſt thou for theſe things? and what Scripture haſt thou for the Word, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Catechiſing, or to premeditate aforehand? and when had any of the Miniſters of Chriſt Studies, as thou ſaiſt thou mightieſt have been quiet in thy Study at home?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116537:11"/>Thou art out of the ſteps of the true Miniſters of Chriſt, expounding and giving meanings to the Scriptures, adding and diminiſhing, interpreting and wreſting the Scriptures: And therefore thy Goſpel is eaſily proved to be another then theirs was; and if thou call us Deceivers or Seducers, prove it by Scripture, That we are ſuch, as draw from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointing within unto outward obſervations; for ſuch are Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers; and he is a Deceiver that tranſgreſſeth, and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and ſteals the Word from his neighbor; that uſeth his tongue, and ſaith, Thus ſaith the Lord, when the Lord never ſent him, among whom thou art found; although thou lean upon the Lord, and with the Phariſee, juſtifie thy ſelf for Preaching many Lectures, and viſiting the ſick; thy long Prayers, and thy Lecture Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is but the divination of thy own brain; and thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Sacrifices, is no more to the Lord then the cutting of a Dogs neck,
<note place="margin">Iſa: 66.3</note> or offering Swines blood, ſo long as thou art not juſtified by Faith; therefore give over Divining for money, and Preaching for hire, and let all fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh be ſilent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord; for he that exalteth himſelf, will the Lord a baſe, and bring down, that no fleſh may glory in his preſence.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>But let me proceed to demand of you ſatisfaction in one thing: Pray how do you prove the Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>preach an other Gospel then.</hi> Paul, <hi>preached? for that was one of your marks of the falſe Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I own and have union with the Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and elſwhere, that declare freely unto others that which they have heard and ſeen, taſted and bandled of the Word of Life;
<note place="margin">1 John 1.1.</note> which they have received neither of man, nor by man, but by the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt; and I have nothing to ſay againſt them: But if either thou, or any other man in <hi>England,</hi> or an Angel from Heaven preach another Goſpel, then that which the Apoſtle preached, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>I receive the Gospel from</hi> Paul, <hi>as the</hi> Galatians <hi>did even from the ſame writings of</hi> Paul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Even as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ſo ſay I to them who believes thy teſtimony, O fooliſh people and unwiſe I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116537:11"/>who hath bewitched you to believe ſuch a lying ſpirit? or to own ſuch a one for your Miniſter. Is it a like thing that <hi>Fra-Fulwood</hi> could receive the Goſpel from <hi>Paul,</hi> as the <hi>Galatians</hi> did? Its manifeſt, that <hi>Paul</hi> had preached the Goſpel to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> before he wrote that Epiſtle to them from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Galatians</hi> had alſo received it, before that Epiſtle was written: And theſe writings are not called the Goſpel, which he ſaith he received the Goſpel from; and if they were, he is found but one of them that ſteal the Word from his neighbor, and from another mans writings: So it is but death and deſtruction that ſpeaks of the ſame; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receive no ſuch into your houſes, neither bid them God ſpeed, leaſt you alſo be partakers with them in their evil deeds; for all ſuch filthy dreamers and men of corrupt mindes, are ſure to have their portion with <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> and their Forefathers and Brethren in iniquity, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> although by this craft they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper for a while, and get much wealth, which is but the wages of unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>Come, come Sir, you have told us, That what you delivered, you have by revelation from Heaven, wherein I tell you, you blaspheme the Lord; you have ſaid to the people, That the falſe Prophets, meaning us in the Miniſtery, deny the light that is in all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is not blaſphemy to declare what I have received by revelation from Heaven; but it is blaſphemy for falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to call themſelves Chriſts Miniſters. For me to declare againſt falſe Prophets, as I am moved of the Lord, is neither blaſphemy nor railing diſcourſe as thou accounteſt it; and in as much as thou denieſt the ſufficiency of the light to lead to ſalvation, or eternally to condemn, thou maiſt apply it to thy ſelf, to be one of thoſe falſe Prophets that rebels againſt the light, <hi>Job</hi> 24.13. whoſe pernitious ways many have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by reaſon of whom the way of truth, is evil ſpoken of; for thou ſayeſt, the light ſpoken of in the Scripture, will be found to be onely common and not ſaving. Here the nature and operation of the light is by thee denied, and the Scripture perverted; and with the light that never changes, art thou comprehended, judged, and condemned.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116537:12"/>
            <p>Chriſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">John 8.12.</note> I am the light of the world, and he that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows me, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life: And Chriſts Miniſters bear teſtimony to the ſame light; and this is the condemnation, That light is come into the world, and men loves darkneſs rather then light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds are evil. For whatſoever is reproved is firſt made manifeſt by the light, and whatſoever makes manifeſt, is light, <hi>Epheſians</hi> chap. 5. And his light turned to, believed in, loved and obeyed, is ſufficient to lead to ſalvation: And for this purpoſe were Chriſts Miniſters ſent forth as ſheep among wolves, to turn men from the darkneſs to the light that ſhined in the darkneſs; which their dark underſtandings did not comprehend, before they heard Preachers that were ſent: and of this light I am a witneſs; and this is the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I have to declare, That God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all; in him was life, and his life was the light of men: And this is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world. The Law of God alſo is called a light, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6 23. and the Commandment a Lamp, and the Word of God is a Light and a Lanthorn, and his Covenant a light, as its written, Behold I will keep thee, and give thee for a Covenant of the people, for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation to the ends of the earth. Chriſt Jeſus is this light, as it is written, Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, according to thy Word; for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation, which thou haſt prepared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of all people, a light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and in vain is ſalvation hoped for from the mountains and from the hills; for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that is mighty, is ſalvation laid, who ſaith, Look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and be ſaved, all ye ends of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>There is no means ſufficient to ſalvation, but what Scripture aſſerts to be ſo; but we do not finde in Scripture, that the light is ſufficient to convince of ſin, if improved; if it be, ſhew it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The grace of God which bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared unto all men; and this grace is ſufficient, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. And the Scripture declares there is no other name given
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116537:12"/>under Heaven, whereby men can be ſaved,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> but by the name of Jeſus, who ſaith, I am the light; and God who command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed light to ſhine out of darkneſs, bath alſo ſhined into our hearts, to give us the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. And we have this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Earthen Veſſels, ſince it hath pleaſed the Father to reveal his Son in us, unto whom he hath freely made known, what is the glory of the Myſtery that hath been hid from ages and gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations, Chriſt in us the hope of glory,
<note place="margin">1 Col. 27.</note> in whom is life, and this life is our light, and this light is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; for that which may be known of God, is manifeſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: But this is a myſtery to you, whoſe wiſdom is earthy, and your underſtandings darkned; and unto ſuch is our Goſpel hid, whoſe mindes the God of this world hath blinded, among whom we have had our converſation in times paſt. But our light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen, and ariſing, and ſhall cover the face of the earth, as the waters cover the Sea. And now the ſinners in <hi>Zion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to tremble, and fearfulneſs ſurpriſes the Hypocrites; the voice of <hi>Babylons</hi> merchants is heard with a loud cry,
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.</note> Alas, alas! for none will buy our merchandiſe any longer. Come ſay they, let us ſmite with the tongue, the hope of our gain is gone; you know that by this craft we have got our wealth, and if theſe mens doctrine be received, not onely our craft is endangered; but our Church and Ordinances which all the world worſhips in, will be denied, and our Tithes, Augmentations, Gifts, and Rewards for Preaching, will be taken away. Report, and we will report it; let us call them Deceivers and Seducers, for none dare contradict us: When we are in the Pulpits, the Law of the Land is our protection, and by it we have liberty to impriſon them, if they diſturb or interrupt us. And thus you Pariſh-Teachers ſhelter your ſelves for a ſeaſon; but your covering is too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and your bed will be found ſhorter then a man can ſtretch himſelf upon it. Your wickedneſs is manifeſt, and reproved by the light; and by a fooliſh people are you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to jealouſie, whom God hath choſen to confound the wiſdom of the wiſe; glory to his Name for ever, who hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116537:13"/>put an end to the firſt Covenant that made not the comers thereunto perfect, as pertaining to the conſcience, and hath diſannulled the Commandment going before, by reaſon of the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs of it. This is our God, we have waited for him; he alone is our Judge, King, and Law-giver, to whom our ſoul is ſubject; for he ever liveth, and hath an unchangable Prieſthood, even him who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, all that come to God by him: Which we now witneſs, and deny, and declare againſt the changable Prieſthood that took Tithes, and denied Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>Tithes are lawful, becauſe not forbidden; yea, they ſeem to be encouraged by Chriſt himſelf; ye. Tithe Mint, &amp;c. And ye do well therefore, we do not ill to take them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Read thy portion among them, to whom Chriſt ſpoke; and if thou do well, mayſt thou not be accepted? Wo unto you Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye pay Tithe of Mint,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> Anniſe, and Cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the Law, Judgment, Mercy, and Faith: Theſe you ought to have done, and not to leave the other undone. But he did not ſay. You did well in ſo doing, but called them fools and bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nde: And ſo may I truly call him who ſaith, this is an encouragement to takes Tithes. If thou or any of thy Brethren take them on this account, for ſhame never profeſs your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel; for Chriſt gave no command or encouragement to the Twelve, Seventy, or to any of his Diſciples to take Tithes: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe to whom Chriſt then ſpake, did not believe in him, nor confeſs him to be the end of the firſt Covenant; in which Tithes was commanded, and due to be paid to the Levitical Prieſthood, which were many Prieſts, becauſe they were not ſuffered to continue by reaſon of death: But this man hath an unchangable Prieſthood; for he ever liveth to make interceſſion for his, and is able to ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, all them that come to the Father by him, who is made a Prieſt for ever, not by the Law of a carnal command, but by the power of an endleſs life; and of the things which are ſpoken,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.1.</note> both concerning <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> and the Levitical
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116537:13"/>Prieſthood, in that Declaration to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> This is the ſum and ſubſtance, Jeſus Chriſt who is ſet on the right hand of the Throne of the Majeſtie in the Heavens, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Sanctuary, and of the true Tabernacle which God hath pitched, and not man.</p>
            <p>For finding fault with the firſt Covenant, Behold the days come, ſaith the Lord, that I will make with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and with the houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> a new Covenant, not according to the old, which Covenant they brake. Even this is the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> After thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their mindes, and write them in their hearts; I will be unto them a God, and they ſhall be my people.</p>
            <p>And thus the Law and Prieſthood being changed, as is clear by Scripture; neither thou, nor thy Brethren have any right to take Tithes, either by the Law of God, or example of Chriſts Miniſters; nor no encouragement from his words, nor from that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who freely gave Tithes to <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec</hi> out of the ſpoils, who bleſſed him when he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Conqueſt; but ye receive the tenth, not of the ſpoils onely, but out of poor mens labors, and of them who receive no bleſſing from you, and for whom you do no work.</p>
            <p>In the time of the Law there were indeed many Prieſts, and the Prieſts lips were to preſerve the knowledge of the people; and then they ought to have brought their Tithes into the ſtorehouſe. And theſe Prieſts had a neceſſity daily to offer Sacrifice; firſt for their own ſin, and then for the peoples: But Chriſt being come, the Everlaſting High Prieſt of good things to come, by a greater and a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Tabernacle, not made with hands as the figures and ſhadows of theſe good things was: He hath obtained a more excellent Miniſtry, in as much as he is the Mediator of a better Covenant, eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes. And ſo the Prieſthood being changed,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.12.</note> there is made of neceſſity a change of the Law.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116537:14"/>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>I have two things to defend our taking of Tithes againſt his Verſe; one of which I am ſure will hold. The firſt is, That we claim not Tithes by the Law of God, as it were commanded there, but by the Law of the Land, whereby we have as clear a title to our Tithes, as that Gentleman hath to his Eſtate. The ſecond thing that I have to ſay, is, That you cannot prove by this Text, that the onely Law for Tithes in the Word of God is aboliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Even upon this ground hath thy generation, whoſe hearts are exerciſed with coveteous practiſes in all ages, cauſed the Saints and Servants of God, of whom the world was not worthy, to ſuffer. Some the ſpoiling of their goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and others the trials of cruel mockings, yea, moreover Bonds and Impriſonments, for bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt their deceit. Here thou haſt manifeſted thy ſelf ſufficiently to be out of Chriſts doctrine and command, as before in this Relation is expreſſed, to wit, Bound by man to Preach every Lords day; and by the Law of man thou receiveſt thy reward. And ſo if thou haſt a minde to ſue any of thoſe that believe in Chriſt at the Law, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Coat, thou maiſt have their Cloak alſo; for they cannot reſiſt thee, being made ſubject to the higher power for Conſcience ſake: And if thou ſmite me on the one Cheek, I muſt rather turn the other, then ſmite thee again. And if any of thoſe within the compaſs of thy quarter, who are witneſſes of the unchangable Prieſthood, out of Conſcience refuſe to pay thee Tithes, thou haſt this ſhelter to flie unto; to wit, the Law of the Land to ſue them for their own Corn or Hay, on which thou never beſtowedſt any labor.</p>
            <p>But Friend, look thou firſt unto the Royal Law, and ſee if this be as thou wouldſt be done by. If thou profeſs thy ſelf to be a Miniſter of God, let the Law of God be thy rule, and take counſel of him alone, and let his Word be thy light; and here thou wilt come to ſee thy pleading for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116537:14"/>Tithes, to be onely for thy own carnal ends, and not for the glory of God: And if any one deny to pay Tithes out of coveteouſneſs, ſelf-ends, or a deſire to ſave the Earth; I am againſt that principle, both in thee and them; For the Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof. And if any man have this worlds goods, and ſee his Brother have need, and ſhut up his compaſſion againſt him; how dwells the love of God in that man?</p>
            <p>But that thou haſt as much right to Tithes, as the Gentleman thou makeſt mention of, hath to his eſtate, it lies upon thee to prove by Scripture;
<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> for that Law is changed, and the hand writing of Ordinances blotted out, by which the Levitical Prieſthood had right to their Tithes, who had no inheritance in the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> But thou canſt not prove, that the Evidences by which the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thou ſpeakeſt of, holds his eſtate, is diſannulled or made void.</p>
            <p>And they who received Tithes,
<note place="margin">Deut. 14.29.</note> had alſo a commandment to pay Tithes: And if thou plead for their order, then the ſtrangers, the widows, and fatherleſs, have as much reaſon to plead for, and right to receive Tithes, as thou or any of thy Brethren hath.</p>
            <p>And if thou plead for <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> order, then if thou meet any coming from the ſlaughter of their enemies, after they have conquered, if thou have a bleſſing for them, thou maiſt take the Tenth of the ſpoils, if they be free to give it thee; but if thou deny the figures, and own and confeſs Jeſus Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and thy ſelf to be one of his Miniſters, thou needſt neither plead for Tithes, nor take thought what to eat or drink, or what to put on:
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> For after theſe things do the Heathen ſeek, who know not God.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>The Text ſaith, he paid Tithes; and if it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, That Tithes be lawful to be paid in the time of the Gospel, I deſire no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116537:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Text doth not ſay, that Tithes was paid in the time of the Goſpel, not to any of the Miniſters of the Goſpel; and if thou confeſs thy ſelf to be one, I demand of thee to what end thou deſiredſt it ſo earneſtly. If thou didſt but take Chriſts counſel, to ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God and its righteouſneſs, all other things would be added unto thee; for God hath ordained, that they that preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel, and be content with food and rayment; and the hand writing of Ordinances for taking Tithes is blotted out, and the Commandment going before diſannulled; ſo that it cannot be granted to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for Chriſts Miniſters to take Tithes: But what needeſt thou be afraid, if thou be one of his? If God took care for Oxen in the time of the Law, and for the Levitical Prieſts, who had no inheritance in the promiſed Land?
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> Doth he not alſo take care for his children in theſe days, ſeeing his mercy endures for ever? O thou of little Faith! is not thy life more then meat, and thy body more then rayment? If thou were but a Miniſter of Chriſt, and didſt watch onely for the ſoul, the diſpute about theſe carnal things would be ſoon at an end; but by the children of light, both your Call, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Maintenance, and Ordinances are ſeen, which ſtands onely in outſide things, and carnal waſhings, are ſeen and judged. What Scripture have you for ſprinkling of Infants, and ſo call it Baptiſm, or an Ordinance of God?</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>I never ſaw an Infant onely ſprinkled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether it be dipping or ſprinkling, prove your Baptiſm of Infants by Scripture to be a lawful command of Chriſt, or an Ordinance of God; elſe I charge you to be uſurpers of Authority: Many are unſatisfied about this Ordiannce, as you call it; therefore it lieth upon you to make full proof of your Miniſtry and practiſe; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your manner of Baptiſing Infants differs in the ground of it from the Prelates, Biſhops, and Papiſts, whoſe doctrine and practiſe you pretend to deny: And when your deeds is brought to the light to be proved, then it will appear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or we have denied the Popiſh Tenants, practiſe and principles.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116537:15"/>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>This is but to delude the people; you know you deny all Baptiſm with water, and that you are as much againſt the Anabaptiſts as againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a falſe accuſation; for I with thouſands more in this Nation, whoſe union and fellowſhip is in the light, do own and witneſs the Baptiſm which the Scripture ſpeaks of, which is by one Spirit into one Body;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13.</note> but all Beggerly Elements, Bodily Exerciſes, Carnal Ordinances, and Outſide Services, Imitations, Likeneſſes, and Shadows of Heavenly things, we count as dung and droſs in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, the Subſtance and End of all Figures, Types and Shadows, in whom we are circumciſed, with the Circumciſion made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, in putting off the Body of the ſins of the fleſh, buried with him in Baptiſm, and raiſed together with him, through the Faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed him from the dead, and we are compleat in him who is the head of all principalities and powers,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> who hath made a ſhew of them openly, triumphing over them; and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world, we are no more ſubject to its Ordinances, knowing that they periſh with the uſing, and do not make the Comers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto perfect; although they have a ſhew of wiſdom, and a will-worſhip in a voluntary humility, by which the people are deluded; and if the Anabaptiſts, as thou calleſt them have an other Baptiſm then this, we are not ſubject unto it. And whereas thou chargeſt me with deluding the people, its falſe, and more then thou canſt prove: But I ſhall paſs by it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving learned of him who when he was reviled, reviled not again. And if thou haſt any Scripture for the baptiſing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants with water, ſhew it for the peoples ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>We are commanded to baptize all Nations; but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are a great part of all Nations: Therefore we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to baptize Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is no mention made of water in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; and beſides, they to whom it was given, were firſt ſent forth to teach; as it is written, <hi>Go teach all Nations;</hi> and they abode in the doctrine of Chriſt, and went forth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116537:16"/>as ſheep among Wolves; and into whatſoever City, Town, or Village they entred, they were to inquire, who was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and not what they might expect for a livelihood for themſelves, their Wives, and their Children: And ſome were ſent forth not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel; and theſe were ſent firſt to teach and preach repentance, and they were to repent before they were to be baptized. So that it plainly manifeſts, That thoſe who baptize Infan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s before they teach them, or before they have repented, are tranſgreſſors of this command of Chriſt. And I alſo queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where ever <hi>Frances Fulwood</hi> was ſent either to preach or baptize; for Chriſts Miniſters were not ſo beggerly, as to take hire for their preaching twice every Lords day, or to contend or wrangle for a competent maintenance in lieu of preaching, or for Tithes, calling them Chriſts wages; This manifeſts another ſpirit then was in the true Prophets, Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt, who called all to come freely, without money, and without price, and gave freely as they had freely received. But as there were falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even ſo there are alſo falſe Prophets in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covercous practiſes; and who have forſaken the right way in theſe laſt days and perilous times; and many have followed their pernicious ways, by reaſon of whom, the way of truth is evil ſpoken of. And theſe men in the ears of deluded people, are cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Church and Ordinances, Baptiſm, Sacrament, Preaching, Praying, and Singing, even as the Jews did of old, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, when they themſelves were even deſtroyed for want of knowledge. But the Lord hath raiſed up a light in the hearts of Ten thouſands of his Saints, whereby they are comprehended, judged, and condemned, and turned away from them that have gotten the words without the life; the form, but not the power; the ſhadow, and not the ſubſtance; the ſign, but not the ſeal. There was indeed a time of ignorance, a day that was neither clear, nor dark; in the which we were led aſide by theſe dumb Idol-ſhepherds, till God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, and ſhined into our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116537:16"/>hearts to give us the light of the knowledge of the glorious Goſpel, Church, and Ordinances, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, of whom we had heard, and on whom we had believed: And being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God;
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> and without faith its impoſſible to pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>Faith you ſay is required in Baptiſm, and that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Infants capable thereof; for though Faith be required, this doth not render Infants uncapable of Baptiſm; for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were capable of Circumciſion, and yet Circumciſion was a ſign and ſeal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Their Circumciſion made with hands was a ſign,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> but not a ſeal; for what ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved God, and it was counted to him for righteouſneſs, not when he was in Circumciſion, but when he was in uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and he received the ſign of Circumciſion, a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of faith, which he had when he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed. The Circumciſion of the heart is the ſeal,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 20.12. &amp; 10.</note> and the Circumciſion with hands was the ſign of that ſeal, as the Sabbath was given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a ſign of that Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sabbath, which is prepared for the people of God. But now, neither Circumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth any thing, but a new Creature; neither doth the figure of Water-baptiſm, nor Sprinkling of Infants which is no figure, ſeal, nor ſign, avail any thing,
<note place="margin">1 Pet 3.21.</note> but the keeping of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; for when the Gentiles that have not the Law, do by nature the things contained in the Law, theſe having not the Law, are a Law unto themſelves,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect of the Law written in their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the uncircumſion keep the righteouſneſs of the Law, ſhall not his uncircumciſion be counted for Circumciſion? for that is not Circumciſion which is outward,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> but that of the heart in the Spirit, and not in the Letter; for they onely are the Circumciſion that worſhip God in the Spirit, and have no confidence in the fleſh, and they only know the true Baptiſm, that are come to the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, who are buried with him in Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note> and quickned together with him, and ſealed up by the Spirit of promiſe, until the day of redemption.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116537:17"/>
            <p>And if this be all the proof can be alleaged for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of Infants, by the Teachers of the World, and their upholders, the Author of this Book, their Foundation is on the Sand; for neither can they prove that Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to baptize Infants with water; nor that it came in the room of circumciſion, or that it is either Sign or Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, unleſs we ſhould believe what they conceive or imagine for a truth, which few will do that have their ſences exerciſed by reaſon of uſe to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween truth and error, the power of godlineſs and the form, and have had experience of the deceit of ſuch as now are gone forth into the world,
<note place="margin">Matth. 15.9.</note> who teach for doctrine the traditions of men.</p>
            <p>Something alſo was ſpoken about ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Rime and Meeter, which I then oppoſed and denied the practiſe of, as they were by theſe Poets or Fidlers, <hi>Stern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Hopkins,</hi> and others, Tranſlated into Engliſh Meeter, with apt Notes to be ſung in the Church and Chappels, ſo called, before their Morning and Evening Prayers, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Preaching; which while the people are ſinging, they uncover their heads; as if the Scriptures were more holy and honorable ſince theſe men perverted them, by putting them into Meeter, then they were before, as they were ſpoken forth by him who was a holy man after Gods own heart, inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But all your Songs will the Lord God of Sabbath ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn into weeping and howling, mourning and bitter la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation: Although for a ſeaſon theſe men of the World, whoſe portion is in this life, may make merry over the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and put far away the evil day; who lie upon their Beds of Ivory, and ſtretch themſelves on the Couches, that eat the Lambs out of the flock, and the Calves out of the midſt of the ſtall, that chant to the ſound of the Viol, and invent to themſelves inſtruments of Muſick like <hi>David,</hi> who ſings lyes in the Name of the Lord, calling him to witneſs that they are not puft in minde, when they are ſo proud, heady, high-minded and ſcornful, that without diſdain they can ſcarcely one look upon another, and eſpecially if any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116537:17"/>that witneſſeth <hi>Davids</hi> conditions come in among them, that cannot bow to their will-worſhip, but ſtand a witneſs againſt them. If they do not ſmite with the fiſt of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they will be ſure to ſmite with the tongue in ſcorn and deriſion, with the name of Quaker, or ſome other invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, reproachful term, as their forefathers, who ſaid they were of <hi>Abraham,</hi> did with Chriſt and his Miniſters, that declared againſt their cuſtoms and traditions; away with ſuch a fellow ſay they, It is not fit he ſhould live upon the earth, he brings in cuſtoms not lawful to be obſerved. You that are guilty, apply this to your ſelves, and be you witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that you are the children of them that killed the Prophets, crucified Chriſt, and perſecuted his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; though you may profeſs their words, and cover your ſelves with their cloathing, their life you are ſtrangers unto; and we are even become your enemies becauſe we tell you the truth. The laſt thing, as it is alſo in the Relation, was about the plain language of Scripture, as <hi>thee</hi> or <hi>thou</hi> to a particular perſon.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>This is but the tranſlation, and it was indifferent for the Tranſlators to have tranſlated it</hi> you <hi>or</hi> thou, <hi>the original will ſuffer either.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let that of God in thy conſcience, and all who know the original, be witneſſes againſt thee for a lier; it had never been written nor tranſlated to the natural mans under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; the original is pure, even the Word of God, which was in the beginning before tranſgreſſion was, and when the world was all of one Language, before the diſperſing of <hi>Babels</hi> builders: And this word is the original, and not the confounded Tongues and Languages of the Nations of this World, that are under the vail yet untaken away; and they that ſpeak not according to this Word, are ſuch as rebel againſt the light; and thoſe who are in darkneſs, call the Hebrew and Greek the Original, and have erred from the right way, not knowing the Scripture, nor the power of God; for the natural man by his faln wiſdom, perceives not the things of the Spirit of God; and evil men and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers are grown worſe and worſe: Therefore its more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116537:18"/>that thoſe who are not come to a perfect underſtanding of the thing that was in the beginning, ſhould believe the Scripture as it is tranſlated, rather then ſuch Dreamers and Diviners as ſet up their ancient Heatheniſh cuſtoms above the Scripture; or the rule declared of in Scripture: Did not God himſelf uſe the ſame expreſſions unto <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> unto him again, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And alſo to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to him again, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. And likewiſe to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> to him again, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. And alſo to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> a true Prophet, and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to him again, <hi>Jere.</hi> 11. And to <hi>Jonah,</hi> and <hi>Jonah</hi> to him again, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4. And Chriſt Jeſus the end of the Prophets, to his Father uſed theſe expreſſions, <hi>John</hi> 17. with a cloud of witneſſes that might be inſtanced, if it were required, that this is the pure Language to one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon.</p>
            <p>Fulw. <hi>Pray let me take occaſion to minde you, when theſe expreſſions of</hi> thee <hi>and</hi> thou <hi>have their uſe in cuſtom; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in two caſes, Firſt, In a way of great familiarneſs, as to our very intimate, or thoſe much below us. Secondly, In way of great reverence and diſtance as to God, and to a Prince; but in neither of theſe ſenſes do you uſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can the Blackmoor change his skin, or the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard his ſpots? then may thoſe who are accuſtomed to lye, and to do evil be changed: Although we do not uſe theſe words as a cuſtom, yet we uſe them with reverence and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear, both unto God, and to our Superiors, Equals, and Inferiors, in love and familiarily, and not with reſpect to the perſons of Princes, or any other that ſeeks honor from men. And thoſe that are our intimate friends in the truth, are not offended at the expreſſion, but they that are at a diſtance, and ſtrangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, and aliens to the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> cry out againſt us, as being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in our Laws and Cuſtoms from all other people. This is a cuſtom not lawful to be obſerved ſay they, Come let us expel them out of our coaſts,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16.</note> theſe contentious men, we have no ſuch cuſtom; theſe familiar expreſſions cannot be borne in our Country: And therefore we deny to contend for ſuch indifferent things as theſe people make conſcience of,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116537:18"/>who place Religion in words; and even thus the brutiſh Paſtor ſlights not onely the words of truth and ſoberneſs, but alſo the weightier matters of the Law which God hath required, Judgment, Mercy, and Humility; and by their lyes and lightneſs have they cauſed many to forſake the right way, and to follow their deviſed fables, traditions, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh cuſtoms, inſtead of true and ſound Doctrine.</p>
            <p>To the ſubſtance of what paſſed that day in the Diſpute, thus much in anſwer in brief, for the Reaſons above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And where as the Relation ſaith, one went one way, and an other another way, as if nothing had been ſpoken but in the Diſpute. It may be taken notice of, that after <hi>Francis Fulwood</hi> and his company was gone, our meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued a pretty ſeaſon, and a door of utterance was given me afterwards, to ſpeak to the people for their further ſatisfaction in things that lay dark, as a difference between us in the diſpute, and ſomething for their further information and edification; and ſo our meeting was for the better, and not for the worſe, and according to order the Aſſembly was diſmiſt at that time.</p>
            <p>Come down and ſit in the duſt, ye Marchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 3.3.</note> and all ye cunning Artificers and eloquent Orators that long have traded with the Saints words, ſit ſilent, and get you into darkneſs; for no more is your perſons to be had in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, becauſe of advantage, Gird your ſelves with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, ye Miniſters of the Letter, and hired Pariſh Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that have long uſed your tongues, and ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ezek 34.</note> Thus faith the Lord, when the Lord never ſpoke unto you. Yet have ſed your ſelves with the fat, and cloathed your ſelves with the wooll; you have drunk of the deep wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and have fouled the reſidue with your ſeet, and the poor of the flock have eaten that which ye have troden down, and drunk that which ye have fouled with your feet. Be ye aſhamed, O ye Husbandmen, for the Seed is even rotten under the clods; weep and howl ye pretended Vine-dreſſers, for the Vineyard is over-grown with thorns, bryers, and fruitleſs Trees; the day of your viſitation is come, the trumpet is ſounded in <hi>Zion,</hi> and an alarum is heard in the holy Mountain of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116537:19"/>Lord. Let all the children of the Weſt tremble, be afraid ye ſinners in <hi>Zion,</hi> and let fearfulneſs take hold of all deceitful hypocrites; the Lords controverſie is againſt the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and Idol-ſhepherd; the ſword ſhall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 11.7.</note> his right arm ſhall be quite dryed up, and his right eye ſhall be utterly darkned; for the Lord is ariſing in his glorious Majeſty, to ſhake terribly the Earth, and to bring down the mighty from their ſeats, and to exalt that of low degree. The time is come, that iniquity ſhall have an end, the Crown ſhall be removed, and the Diadem taken away; the thrones of iniquity ſhall be caſt down, that the antient of days may ſit, to whom all judgement is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; the government muſt be upon his ſhoulders, that he alone may rule and reign, even the Captain of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and Prince of our Peace, who is King of Kings and Lord of Lords, God over all, bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>The flying Angel is gone forth with the Everlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. 14.</note> to preach unto all Kinreds, Tongues, and Languages of the Nations; and unto you hath the Call reached, that long hath groaned under the dominion and oppreſſion of the Prince of the air; the hour cometh, and now is, in the which the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God; and he that heareth ſhall live. Ariſe and ſhine, for you light is come, you that long have ſlept in the duſt of the earth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of deliverance: Come forth of the priſon houſes, ſhew your ſelves; ſalvation and ſtrength is come, the Kingdom of our God, and the power of his Chriſt; the knowledge of the glory of God is ariſing that ſhall cover the face of the Earth, as the waters cover the Sea: Seek not ye the living among the dead; for in vain is ſalvation hoped for or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Mountains, or from the Hills; it is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that is mighty, even able to ſave to the uttermoſt, all thoſe that come to the Father by him. Therefore ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, and heap not up unto your ſelves Teachers, believe not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, for many falſe Prophets are gone forth into the world in theſe laſt days and perilous times: But God who at ſundry times, and divers manners, ſpake to the Fathers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116537:19"/>by his ſervants, the true Prophets, hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken by his Son, whom he hath appointed to be heir of all things, by whom alſo he made the world, whoſe day <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſaw and rejoyced; of whom he hath ſaid, Let all the Angels of God worſhip him; And if the word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and every tranſgreſſion and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, received a juſt recompence of reward, how can ye eſcape, who neglect this great ſalvation. O that you knew in this your day the things that belong unto your peace, which ſo long have been hid from your eyes: A Prophet hath God raiſed up unto you like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Paſtors hath he ſent forth according to his own heart; riſing up early, and ſitting down late, ſaying, Turn ye, turn ye, why will you die? He that hath an ear, let him hear; this is the day of <hi>Zions</hi> deliverance, the Lord is gathering in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the diſperſed from among the Gentiles; and out of the heaps of rubbiſh is he raiſing up living ſtones to build unto himſelf a Spiritual houſe; and other Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can no man lay then that which is already laid, Jeſus Chriſt, the Rock of Ages, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, who is now come a light into the world; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever believeth on him ſhall never be aſhamed. This is our God, we have waited for him, who by his own arm hath brought Salvation and plenteous Redemption, who came and preached peace to us, that ſometimes were afar off, and hath ſhined into our hearts by the light of the glorious Goſpel, and hath made us nigh by the blood of the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant: To whom be glory and honor through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Salthouſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116537:20"/>
            <p>IF <hi>Ja. Godfreys</hi> Queries to <hi>Geo. Pitt,</hi> which is added to this Relation, had been all anſwered; then <hi>F. F.</hi> might have expected an anſwer to his Counter-queries; but I ſhall leave them to him to whom they were directed, That if he ſee any thing worth an anſwer, he may write to it, if he be free. And ſeeing they are of ſo little weight, ariſing onely from a buſie minde,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.</note> I ſhall take the counſel of ſuch a one as <hi>Paul</hi> the aged in this particular, to ſhun prophane and vain bablings, which genders ſtrife, and tends to more ungodlineſs, not doting about queſtions and ſtrife of words, whereof cometh envies, evil furmiſing, and perverſe diſputing with men of corrupt mindes, reprobate concerning the Faith, and deſtitute of the truth, who do ſuppoſe that gain is godlineſs. But to me it is no advantage to fight with Beaſts, if the dead do not riſe; neither would I be found as one beating the air, or boaſting in another mans line, or anſwering a fool in his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: But if any ask a reaſon of the hope that is in me, I am and ſhall be ready with meekneſs and fear, to give an anſwer as God gives a mouth and wiſdom, whoſe counſel and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection I ſtill wait for. And ſo unto him in weldoing I commit the keeping of my ſoul, as unto a faithful Creator.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Salthouſe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116537:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
